BirthNet; Records apap402
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
BirthNet Records
1994-2020
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap402
5.42 cubic ft.
This collection documents the founding and day-to-day activities of BirthNet, a birth justice organization located in the Capital District of New York.
Content Description
This collection contains administrative records, including meeting and annual meeting files, organizing files; clips, publications; correspondence; partnership files; subject files; and advocacy files.
Access
Access to this collection is restricted because it is unprocessed. Portions of the collection may contain recent administrative records and/or personally identifiable information. Please contact an archivist for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were donated by Carolyn Keefe in March 2023.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically into three series as follows:
1: Administrative Files, 1994-2020, Undated 2: Public Education, 1995-2018, Undated 3: Events and Workshops, 1999-2018, Undated
Historical Note
BirthNet is a birth justice organization founded in 2001 that serves the Albany, New York area, including the communitities of Troy, Schenectady, Rensselaer, Latham, Colonie, Saratoga, and East and North Greenbush. BirthNet's mission is to ensure that all families receive respectful and appropriate maternity and infant care and to eradicate the inequities in birth outcomes for all childbearing people and birthing situations caused by healthcare discrimination. The purpose is to educate women and their families about all of their birthing options, including midwifery care and homebirth, along with the risks of medical interventions during childbirth. BirthNet is an advocacy organization that connects people with supportive resources, community events, and doula and midwifery services in the Capital Region of New York. BirthNet envisions a community that is centered on personalized care that is culturally appropriate and results in optimal health outcomes. The goals are to place women back into positions of control during childbirth, and to view pregnancy and childbirth as a natural process instead of a medical condition. Maternal mortality rates and the prevention of pregnancy-related death is a key concern for BirthNet. BirthNet intends to push back against the historically racist gynecological profession and empower BIPOC individuals through their programs. Access to education and tools to promote positive birthing experiences regardless of size, gender, sexuality, orientation, and family or cultural structure is encouraged by the organization. BirthNet created partnerships with other organizations for birth education and advocacy, such as the International Cesarean Awareness Network (ICAN), Citizens for Midwifery, and the Coalition for Improving Maternity Services (CIMS). BirthNet began working on Birth Justice initiatives in Albany in 2017 to address healthcare disparities. In 2019, BirthNet held the first doula training program in the Capital District.
BirthNet (Albany, New York); Midwives--New York (State); Feminism--New York (State); Patient advocacy--New York (State); Childbirth--New York (State); Medicine and Health Care; Women; Correspondence; Publications
- Administrative, 1994-2020; 1; 1.28 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains founding materials, research statistics, meeting notes and event reports, legislative proposals and financial and budgeting materials.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Local Statistics, 1994; 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department of Health Statistics, Freedom of Information Act Requests, 1996-1997; 2003; 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2002 Annual Meeting, 1997; 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Materials Development, 1999-2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Coalition Building, 2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Statement of Purpose/Brochure, Visions and Goals, 2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meeting, 2000-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Orientation Materials, 2000-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - BirthNet Meeting Notes (1 of 2), 2000-2016; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - BirthNet Meeting Notes (2 of 2), 2000-2016; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, 2000-2003; 2005-2007; 2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - BirthWatch, 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Trainings to Set Up Non-Profit, 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Event Reports, 2001-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Budgeting Materials, 2001-2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Contracts, 2001; 2003; 2008; 2016 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bylaws, 2002; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2003 Annual Meeting, 2002-2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting, 2003-2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Data Analysis, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Website Planning, 2003-2005; 2007; 2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bringin in Da Spirit Financial Info, 2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2005 Annual Meeting, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Institutes of Health Conference Material Request, 2004; 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Burdett Care Center: Public Health Commission Testimony and Follow-Up, 2004; 2009-2010; 2020; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - GAC Staff Meeting Notes, 2007-2008; 2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - State by State Proposal, 2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Midwifery Modernization Act Letters, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - BCC Pre-Testimony Meeting Notes, 2009-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Free Our Midwives: Midwifery Modernization Act Consumers, 2009-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Midwifery Modernization Act, Freedom Fiesta, 2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Burdett Care Center Forums and Follow Up, 2010-2014 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Website Redesign, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - New York State Midwifery Birth Center Law, 2014; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - New York State Midwifery Birth Center Bill and Regulation, 2015; 2019 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 2005 Annual Meeting, Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - Binder A: Early Programs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Binder A: Handouts Developed by BirthNet, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Statistical Information Formatted by BirthNet, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Binder B: Other New York State Materials, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Binder B: Partners Across New York State, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Binder C: Other National Partners, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Logo/Brochure Ideas, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Public Education, 1995-2018; 2; 2.07 cubic ft.
  This series contains information from media events, partnerships such as Citizens for Midwifery and the Coalition for Improving Maternity Services, PR and marketing materials, and related news articles.
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  - BirthNet Media Folder, 1995-1998; 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Perspectives on Childbirth, 1996-1997; 1999-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services, 1996; 2001-2004; 2008; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ina May Gaskin PR and Marketing, 1996; 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Citizens for Midwifery, 1996; 2003; 2005-2006; 2009; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Having a Baby in the Capital District, 1997; 2021 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Citizens for Midwifery, 1998-2003; 2005-2006; 2008-2009; 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Evidence Based Maternal Care: Bellevue, 1998; 2002-2003; 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Childbirth Connection, 1999; 2002; 2004; 2006-2011; 2013-2015 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Maternity and Childbirth Education, 1999-2005; 2007-2008; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - BirthNet Interviews, 2000-2001 (Cassette 1)
  - Media Talking Points and Prep Info, 2000-2002; 2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to the Editor, 2000-2003; 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services: Public Education and Birth Networks, 2000; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services Materials, Mother Friendly Childbirth Initiative, 2000-2004; 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - BirthNet on Roundtable, 2001 (Cassette 2)
  - Midwife Directory, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - VBAC Program, Saratoga, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Press Releases, 2001-2003; 2005-2006; 2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Articles About BirthNet, 2001-2003; 2005; 2010-2011; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Articles by BirthNet Members, 2001; 2003; 2006; 2014-2015; 2017 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Broadcast Media, TV and Radio, 2001; 2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Local Birth Related Articles, 2001; 2012-2013; 2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - BirthNet Brochure, 2002 (Cd 1)
  - BirthNet/NYFOM on WRPI, 2002 (Cassette 3)
  - BirthNet on WAMC Roundtable, 2002 (Cassette 4)
  - BirthNet on WRPI, 2002 (Cassette 5)
  - "Planting Seeds, Pulling Weeds", 2002 (Cassette 6)
  - New York State Perinatal Network, 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Maternal Infant Network of the Capital Region, 2002-2003; 2006 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Citizens for Midwifery News Article Drafts, 2002-2004; 2008-2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services PR Committee, 2002-2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mother Friendly Childbirth Initiative Information, 2002-2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - New York Birth Coalition, 2002; 2005; 2007-2008; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - BirthNet WTEN Healthy Lifestyles, 2003 (Video-tape 1)
  - WTEN Healthy Lifestyle Segment, 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Family Planning Advocates Meetings, 2003-2005; 2008-2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bringin in Da Spirit Production, 2003; 2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Albany Perinatal Committee, 2003-2006; 2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Maureen May Book Chapter-New York Midwives, 2004; 2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - International Cesarean Awareness Network, 2004; 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Discussion Series, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Breastfeeding Support, 2005; 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Childbirth: A Women's Issue, 2005; 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Birth: A Play by Karen Brody PR and Media, 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mother Friendly Childbirth Initiative Evidence Based Fact Sheet Project, 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Community Cradle, 2007-2008; 2011; Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Regional Breast Feeding Coalition, 2007-2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - BirthNet Presentation, 2008 (Cd 2)
  - Misc. Partnership, 2008-2009; 2015; 2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services: One Voice Organization Members, 2008-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Birthing Choices Presentation, 2010 (Cd 3)
  - Bellies, Babies, and Breasts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Binder A: Handouts BirthNet Used from Other Organizations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Binder A: Materials about BirthNet, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Binder A: Resources Shared by BirthNet, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Binder B: Breastfeeding Support, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Binder B:Coalition for Improving Maternity Services and Mother Friendly Childbirth Initiative, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Binder B: Local Doula and Childbirth Education Practices, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Binder B: Local Midwifery Practices, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Binder B: New York Friends of Midwives, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Binder B: Other Support Organizations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Binder B: Perinatal Network and Albany Perinatal Committee, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Binder C: Citizens for Midwifery and the Midwives Model of Care, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Binder C: International Cesarean Awareness Network, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Binder C: Lamaze International and Birth Networks, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Binder C: Maternity Center Association/Choices in Childbirth, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Binder D: About Interventions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Binder D: About Evidence Based Birth, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Binder D: Birth Professions-Midwifery and Labor Support, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Binder D: Historical Info, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Binder D: Issues with Maternity Care, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Binder D: Reproductive Rights, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Handout Drafts, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Media by and About BirthNet, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Upstate Edition, Undated (Video-tape 2)
- Events and Workshops, 1999-2020; 3; 2.07 cubic ft.
  This series includes reports from national conferences and conventions regarding women's healthcare, feedback from local workshops at schools and in the community, and marketing materials for public community events.
  - UAlbany Sexuality Week: Violation of Women in Childbirth, 1999; 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Binder A: BirthNet Events, 2000-2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WSS 101 and Women/BioHealth Planning, 2000-2003; 2005; 2007; 2009-2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Women's Studies 101, 2000; 2002-2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Midwives Day Pin, 2000 (Artifact-box 1)
  - Healthy Community Expo, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - MANA Region 2, 2001 (Cassette 1)
  - Women's Building Workshop 1 (1 of 2), 2001 (Cassette 2)
  - Women's Building Workshop 1 (2 of 2), 2001 (Cassette 3)
  - Midwives of North America Region Conference, 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women's Building Workshop No. 1, 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women's Studies 101, 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Midwives Alliance of North America Conference, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's Building Workshop, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women's Building Workshop No. 2, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New York State National Organization for Women Conventions, 2001-2002; 2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Women's Studies Class Materials, 2001-2004; 2006; 2011-2012; 2017 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family Planning Advocates Conference (1 of 2), 2001-2008; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Family Planning Advocates Conference (2 of 2), 2001-2008; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Regional Perinatal Forum, 2001; 2005; 2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services Forum, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Women's Building Workshop 2, 2002 (Cassette 4)
  - BirthNet Workshop, Midwives Alliance of North America, 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women's Building Workshop No. 3, 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women's Building Workshop No. 4, 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Women's Studies 101, 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Women's Health Expo, 2002-2009; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York State Association of Licensed Midwives 2010 Lobby Day, 2002; 2006; 2009-2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ina May Gaskin, 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services Forum, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bringing in Da Spirit, 2003-2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Assoc. of Perinatal Networks Symposium and Report, 2003-2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Ina May Gaskin Workshop, 2003; 2005; Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New York State Association of Licensed Midwives 2005 Lobby Day, 2003; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York State National Organization for Women Convention, 2003; 2005-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - National Advocates for Pregnant Women Summit, 2004; 2006; 2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services 2006 Forum, 2004-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Transforming Maternity Care Symposium (1 of 2), 2004; 2008-2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Transforming Maternity Care Symposium (2 of 2), 2004; 2008-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services 2005 Forum, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services 2007 Forum, 2006-2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Orgasmic Birth Film Presentation, 2006; 2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Birth: A Play By Karen Brody, 2007 (Dvd 1)
  - Birth: A Play By Karen Brody, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Birth on Labor Day 2007, General Info., Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Birth on Labor Day Programs, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Birth on Labor Day Script, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Birth on Labor Day Sponsorship, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Business of Being Born, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Cesarean Awareness Network Conference, 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Coalition for Improving Maternity Services 2008 Forum, 2007-2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Workshop and PowerPoint Prep, 2007-2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Birth on Labor Day Truth Initiative, 2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Red Tent, 2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - New York Friends of Midwives: New York State Association of Licensed Midwives 2009 Lobby Day, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Saratoga Women's Fest/Business of Being Born, 2009; 2011; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Institutes of Health Conference: VBAC, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ICAN Discussion, 2011; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Community Festivals/Exhibits, 2011-2016 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Birth Story Film, 2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ina May Gaskin Celebration, 2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - BirthNet 15th Birthday Bash, 2015-2016; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New York State Association of Licensed Midwives Lobby Day, 2015-2016; Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mama Sherpas Event, 2016; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - GAC Webinar Prep, 2020; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Birth: A Play By Karen Brody, Undated (Flat-file 2)
  - Business of Being Born at the Linda, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Red Tent Signs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Women's Studies 101 Responses, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)